Well, first Corinthians chapter 15,
first Corinthians chapter number 15.
Once you've found your place there,
if you'd also find your place in the book of Genesis
and chapter number 39,
Genesis chapter number 39 will be in both of those passages.
We'll look at a couple of other verses as well this morning.
But as we look here in first Corinthians chapter 15,
I'll read just two verses for you
and jump into the message this morning.
And so first Corinthians chapter 15,
and then also Genesis chapter number 39
and we'll spend the bulk of our time this morning
in the book of Genesis and the 39th chapter.
In the New Testament,
the apostle Paul's writing to the church in Corinth.
And there's many things that we know
about this church in Corinth.
We know that they were a very gifted church.
The Bible tells us in the beginning chapters
of this particular book,
that they came behind no other church
and gifts and spiritual gifts,
but we understand they were carnal
and much instruction is given to this church
and the people here in Corinth.
And unfortunately, they had allowed the culture
to influence the church.
And we understand that the church is supposed to,
by God's design to influence the culture,
but how often we find not only in biblical times,
but throughout church history,
if we're not careful,
the culture will influence the church.
And it's important that we as the light of the world,
that we're to shine
and we're to make a difference in our society.
We find this Paul is coming near the end,
of course, the 15th chapter is known
as the resurrection chapter
and what great content that we have here.
But in verse 33, the apostle Paul says this,
be not deceived.
And when a verse of scripture starts that way,
you ought to take note,
you ought to kind of have your ears perked up a little bit
because what he's going to tell us
is really a trap of many people being deceived
with these ideas or these thoughts.
And we read such of such verses
in various places throughout the Bible,
but we find that Paul says, be not deceived.
Evil communications corrupt good manners.
Now, any good parent will tell their children
about the influence of others.
And they'll try to encourage their children
to make sure that they have the right friends.
It's more important to have the right friends
than to have a lot of friends, amen.
A lot of people today, all concerned on social media,
they got all these friends and followers
and all these whatever, they don't know the people,
they just call them friends and the influence is great,
but we definitely need to understand
the principle that we find in verse number 33
that God gives us through the written pen
of the apostle Paul.
But then we come to verse 34
and it's really the focus of our message this morning.
Notice what the Bible says,
awake to righteousness and sin not.
For some have not the knowledge of God,
I speak this to your shame.
And I really wanna focus on the first part
of verse number 34 where the Bible says,
awake to righteousness and sin not.
I think each of us here this morning would agree
that there's a difference between being awake
and being asleep, amen.
I hope you're all awake right now, amen.
And I hope you don't go to sleep on me this morning,
praise the Lord.
But here's the idea, we easily acknowledge
there's a difference between being awake and being asleep.
But I want you to understand there's a difference
between being awake and fully awake and alert
versus being drowsy.
We've said it at different times and different context
and most recently, I believe it was on Father's Day,
I made the statement that dad's fathers,
they can't fall asleep at the wheel.
We kind of use that phrase, that expression, if you will,
to talk about the importance of being alert,
being awake and not being drowsy.
How many of you know when you're drowsy,
you're not as quick as you are when you're fully awake?
Somebody walked in here this morning and I said,
how are you?
And they said, well, look, I'm about 50-50,
I need to get some coffee.
And some of you could relate with somebody
that has that perspective, I like coffee,
but honestly, coffee doesn't really do anything
to help me be awake.
I can drink a cup of coffee and go to sleep
just a few minutes later,
and I know that for some of you, you can't do that,
but you find that there's this difference
between being awake and alert and responsive,
even from being asleep, but I would say also
from being drowsy and just kind of being lethargic,
if you will, and just not being as responsive
as we need to be.
Here we find that the word, when the Apostle Paul,
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
says awake to righteousness, that word awake means to,
we find that it carries with it the idea of returning
to a soberness of mind.
Returning to a soberness of mind.
How many of you know that there's a battle for the mind?
There's a battle for the mind,
and we find that throughout the scriptures,
and I'll be preaching this evening from Psalm 19,
there's the truth with regard to the renewing of our mind.
The Bible tells us in Philippians four
to think on these things, and we understand
that there's a battle for your mind,
and the word awake means literally
a return to soberness of mind.
But we find that the Apostle Paul,
under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit of God,
he doesn't just say wake up, he doesn't just say awake,
he says awake to righteousness.
That's important for us to understand
what God is telling us, that which is just,
that which is upright, that which is proper.
We find that he says awake to righteousness and sin not.
I would submit to you this morning
that though we still have the flesh,
and we still have the old man,
if you're saved here this morning,
and you've trusted Jesus Christ as your personal savior,
you can rejoice as we find in Romans six
and verse number 14, that sin no longer
has dominion over us.
But if you've been saved for any length of time,
you know that you still have the flesh.
And you know, as we're told in the book of Galatians,
that the flesh and the spirit are at enmity
one to the other.
And you understand that in the book of Ephesians,
the book of Colossians, that God gives us
the principle of putting off the old man
and putting on the new man.
The Apostle Paul would describe it this way
in his own life, in the book of Galatians,
he said I am crucified with Christ.
He would then say to the church
and there in the book of Colossians,
he would tell them to mortify their members.
We find that he's writing in the book of Romans
that he would say that they're to present
their bodies a living sacrifice.
And we find that as the Apostle Paul
would set forth that example for us,
and he says here, awake to righteousness and sin not.
The reality is as believers, we'll never reach
a place of sinless perfection.
I'm thankful that one day I will be with my Savior
face to face and no longer will there be the presence
or the possibility of sin.
Until that day, awake to righteousness and sin not.
Now we will not reach a place of sinless perfection,
but we ought to sin less and less
as we walk with the Lord.
If you think you've reached a place of sinless perfection,
let me help you with the Bible truth.
The Bible says if any man says that he does not have sin,
he is a liar.
How do you like that one?
And very forward, amen.
And he says that the truth is not in you.
And then he says this, that you make God a liar.
Just read 1 John chapter number one,
and you'll read those truths.
So the reality is that we're to awake to righteousness
and sin not.
And I'm reminded of what the psalmist said in Psalm four,
in verse number four, when he said stand in awe
and sin not.
Stand in awe and sin not.
Begin to think about these truths that we find here
in 1 Corinthians 15, and I wanna just draw your attention
to two other New Testament principles
before we find ourselves in the book of Genesis this morning.
1 Thessalonians chapter number five.
I want you to notice in this portion of scripture
that the church in Thessalonica has been instructed
with regard to end times,
just dealing with at the end of chapter four,
that wonderful teaching of the rapture.
And I'm so thankful that one day,
and I believe one day soon,
the trumpet of the Lord is going to sound
and we shall be with him,
and we'll be with him for all of eternity.
And we praise the Lord for that.
We go into the fifth chapter of the book of 1 Thessalonians
and the instruction continues to be given here
to this church.
And I want you to notice in verse six,
1 Thessalonians five, it says,
therefore, let us not sleep as do others,
but let us watch and be sober.
You see that word sober again,
and that idea of awake.
Remember, we mentioned that it's that,
oh, returning to a soberness of mind.
So Paul, it's not that you don't sleep.
Obviously, we know we need sleep physically,
but don't be asleep spiritually.
Don't be disconnected.
Don't be lethargic.
Don't be in that place where you're drowsy spiritually.
And he says, let us not sleep as do others,
but let us watch and be sober.
Someone who's watching and is sober,
they're alert and they're prepared.
And we find the instruction here in the book of Titus,
just a few pages over in the book of Titus.
Notice in chapter number two of the book of Titus.
In Titus chapter number two.
Paul here giving instruction to Titus, and he'd have the opportunity to be able to be
there in Crete and to set in order the things that we're wanting as we read the opening
statements of that particular, or this particular letter.
And we come to Titus chapter 2 and verse number 11, and I love the verse, the Bible says,
for the grace of God that bringeth salvation hath appeared to all men.
Aren't you thankful for the grace of God that bringeth salvation?
The Bible says it has appeared to all men, we understand, for by grace are you saved
through faith, and that not of yourselves, it is the gift of God, not of works, lest
any man should boast.
And I'm thankful that our God is gracious, and I'm thankful that His grace hath appeared
to all men, and it's His grace that brings salvation.
But I want you to notice verse number 12, the Bible says, teaching us, that same grace
that brings salvation, after you're saved, it teaches us some things, and notice, teaches
us that denying ungodliness and worldly lust, notice how we should live.
We should live soberly, righteously, and godly in this present world.
Can I tell you this morning, we need some people in 2026 that are gonna awake to righteousness,
that are gonna determine with God's help and by God's grace that they will serve the Lord
and they will deal with the subject of sin seriously.
Someone said this, sin is different in the life of a believer versus an unbeliever, and
they were trying to make really justification for their sin in their lives, the believer,
they were talking to their pastor about it, so you know, you preach about that sin, but
I'm saved, and it's different now, and the pastor, the preacher responded back and said,
yes, it's worse.
I want you to think about that.
Listen, when, we understand we're born sinners, we understand we're at enmity with God, we
understand that we're separated, we need to be reconciled, but after we're saved, you
know, sin in the life of a believer, it hinders that fellowship that we have with God.
The Bible says, if I regard iniquity in my heart, the Lord will not hear me.
Listen, I believe it was a preacher of yesteryear, I think it was Luther that said this, maybe
it was Moody actually that said it, but he said that sin will keep you from this book,
or this book will keep you from sin.
I believe there's a direct connection with this idea of awake to righteousness and sin
not, this idea in the Psalms of stand in awe, when we really see God in His rightful place,
high, holy, and lifted up, it will have impact on you and on me and how we live our lives,
seeking to please Him and honor Him and to walk in righteousness.
In Genesis chapter 39, we're going to look at a passage of scripture here, we'll actually
look at the entire chapter.
I've titled the message this morning simply there from 1 Corinthians 15 and verse number
34, awake to righteousness and sin not.
Many of you are familiar with the life here of Joseph, and at this particular time as
we come to Genesis chapter 39, we understand he's already been sold into slavery there
in Egypt, and we understand that he's now in the house of Potiphar, and he's been bought
by Potiphar, he's now there, and the Bible says in verse number 1, we'll just begin picking
it up, kind of get some backdrop here as we dig into the message, and Joseph was brought
down to Egypt, and Potiphar, an officer of Pharaoh, captain of the guard, an Egyptian,
bought him of the hands of the Ishmaelites, which had brought him down thither.
I want you to notice what it says in verse 2, and the Lord was with Joseph.
Aren't you thankful that our God is omnipresent?
Though he was separated from everyone that he knew, everything that he was familiar with,
he finds himself in Egypt, and the Bible tells us that the Lord was with Joseph, and it says
that he was a prosperous man, he was in the house of his master, the Egyptian, and his
master saw that the Lord was with him.
And I pause again and tell you that if you truly walk with God, other people can see
it.
They can know.
Do you remember the disciples, they stood there before the religious leaders in Acts
chapter number 4, and the Bible says that those religious leaders, when they heard Peter
and John, and they saw what was going on, they had the perception that they were unlearned
and ignorant men.
They said this, but they had been with Jesus, praise the Lord.
And here it says that his master, this is Potiphar, saw that the Lord was with him,
that the Lord made all that he did to prosper in his hand.
Do you recognize God's goodness in your life?
It's all about God.
Amen?
It's that he must increase, and we must decrease.
And it was God that allowed Joseph to have that prosperity and that blessing, and we
find that it's acknowledged in verse number 3, and Joseph found grace in his sight, and
he served him, and he made him overseer over his house, and all that he had he put into
his hand.
And it came to pass in the time that he made him overseer in his house, and over all that
he had, that the Lord blessed the Egyptian's house for Joseph's sake, and the blessing
of the Lord was upon all that he had in the house and in the field.
And he, that's Potiphar, left all that he had in Joseph's hand, and he knew not all
that he had, save the bread which he did eat, and Joseph was a goodly person and well-favored.
And so you get the backdrop here for what's going on within the life of Joseph.
Again, he's sold into slavery, of course his brothers had determined they were gonna kill
him, but then they thought that they could sell him and they could get some gain, and
they lied to their father about what was going on with Joseph.
And Joseph is here in this foreign land, he's in Egypt, this polytheistic nation, and we
find that Joseph finds himself in Potiphar's house and everything seems to be going well
as you read through verse number six of Genesis 39.
But all of a sudden, things are gonna change and they're gonna change drastically.
If you're taking notes this morning, I want you to notice in verses seven through ten
number one, I want you to notice the recognition.
The recognition, when I talk about the recognition, it's what Joseph recognized as we go through
and walk through these verses of Scripture, we'll find that there's three things specifically
that Joseph recognized.
Right away we find, number one, that he recognized the seduction.
The Bible says in verse number seven, notice it says, and it came to pass after these things.
Again, things were going well, there was blessing, there was provision, and it says after these
things that his master's wife cast her eyes upon Joseph and she said, lie with me.
And the seduction was pointed, there was no, there was no beating around the bush,
there was nothing that was unclear about the seduction of Potiphar's wife, and the Bible
says that she said very plainly at the end of verse number seven, lie with me.
He recognized what it was, he recognized the seduction, he recognized that it was pointed.
But I want you to understand that the Scriptures reveal to us that not only was it pointed,
but it was persistent.
Look in verse number 10, it says, and it came to pass as she spake to Joseph, and then notice
those words, day by day, day by day, that he hearkened not unto her to lie by her or
to be with her.
And so we find that right away as things begin to change in the life of Joseph as he's there
in the house of Potiphar and it seems as if everything's going well, and by the way, on
the mountaintop, you better be careful.
In the time of blessing, you better be careful.
You better understand that we have an enemy and we're to be sober and to be vigilant because
your adversary the devil is a roaring lion, walketh about seeking whom he may devour.
We understand that the Bible tells us in Ephesians chapter six that we're to put on the whole
armor of God.
I preached a message about that just a few weeks ago, and there in that message and in
that text of Scripture in Ephesians six, you find that the Bible tells us that we're to
take the shield of faith and with that shield of faith we'll be able to quench all, not
most, not some, but all the fiery darts of the enemy.
And I'm so thankful that God has given to us the provision and the instruction.
He tells us that we're not ignorant of his devices.
Listen, Joseph was here, he didn't have the whole Bible like we have, but he recognized
something.
He recognized something.
He walked with God.
Again, he didn't have the Bible like we have, but he's a man that as you study his life,
he's a man that was spiritual, he's a man that was used of the Lord, and he recognized
the seduction.
But I want you to notice that not only did he recognize the seduction, he recognized
the severity.
He recognized the severity.
The Bible tells us, look at what Joseph says in verse number nine, it says, there is none
greater in this house than I.
Neither hath he kept back anything from me but thee, because thou art his wife.
But then I want you to notice how things change and shift here with regard to the perspective
of Joseph and what he recognized.
At the end of verse number nine, he says, how then can I do this great wickedness?
We're gonna finish the verse in just a moment, but I want you to understand the severity.
I wonder this morning as we begin to think about this idea of sin and we look at what's
going on, see there's sometimes that we're deceived by the enemy.
There's sometimes that we're deceived by others.
Remember, before God told Paul to write, awake to righteousness and sin not, he said, be
not deceived.
Evil communications corrupt good manners.
And we find here this morning that sometimes we kinda sugarcoat sin.
don't make it sound as bad as it really is, but it's an offense to a holy God. Amen?
And we find that sin is serious. It's serious in the life of a believer. Sin, the book of
Hebrews tells us that sin is deceitful. It is deceptive. Here's what happens sometimes.
We begin to think about sin. Sometimes you've heard somebody say this, well it was just
a little white lie. You ever hear somebody say that? Listen, a lie is a lie. And the
Bible says all men are liars. Amen? And it says all liars shall have their part in the
lake which burneth with fire and brimstone. I mean it's serious. It's an offense against
God. We find that at times someone will begin to not see the severity. Joseph calls it great
wickedness. Great wickedness. And we find that sometimes someone will go down a path
and they'll begin to maybe dabble in sin at some level and they don't have judgment
that takes place in their life immediately. And what begins to happen is they begin to
deceive themselves and sin is deceptive as well and they begin to misunderstand the long
suffering of God and they begin to think that God's long suffering, they mistake it with
being God's approval. Can I tell you this morning that God is never okay with sin. Never.
Never. Whoso covereth his sin shall not prosper. Amen? Whoso confesseth and forsaketh, they're
going to have mercy. Praise God for that. I'm thankful that our God is ready to pardon.
He is a God that with thee is forgiveness. He said that if we sin, we confess our sins
that he is faithful and just to forgive us and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.
But we see here that Joseph, he recognized some things. He recognized the severity. He
said it's great wickedness. It's not just a little mistake. It's not just a little slip
up. It's not an error. No, he calls it great wickedness. We not only see that he recognized
the seduction and the severity, but I want you to notice, and it's so vital that we understand
this, that he recognized the sovereign God. Notice what it says at the end of verse number
9. I told you that we'd get back there in just a moment. He says, how then can I do
this great wickedness? Notice what he says, and sin against God. Let me ask you this morning,
would it be a sin against Potiphar? Absolutely. Would it be a sin against Potiphar's wife?
Absolutely. But you know what Joseph recognized? It's a sin against God. It's a sin against
God. We need to understand that as we look at the portion of Scripture and we see the
example of Joseph here, and we understand what he recognized, that he recognized the
sovereign God. Listen, there's nowhere that you can go, there's nowhere that I can go
that God is not there. There's nothing that you can do, there's nothing that I can do
that God does not see and is not aware of. Amen? Listen, Joseph, from a human perspective,
Joseph is in Egypt. Joseph is separated from all that he knew. Everything that he was familiar
with he is separated from, except God. And he knew that God was there. And I believe
the key for this passage of Scripture, something that's so vital for us to understand, is that
Joseph daily lived in the presence of God. He lived in the presence of God. You know
what some people do? They think that they can get into a place of secrecy, if you will.
They can get into a place, they maybe take a phone and they have things hidden on their
phone. They have maybe a place of solitude where they can get alone and they think no
one else is around, no one's ever gonna find out. No, listen, God knows. In fact, just
a little while earlier, you think about the situation with the idols that were taken.
Laban was hot, he was upset, and he goes in and he's gonna try to find those idols, those
images, and guess what? God knew who had them. They were hidden in the tent. Laban never
found them. But God tells us all about it. Achan, he thought, I can get away with it,
surely. I'll just hide it. No one's gonna know. And what happens in Joshua chapter
number 7, God says to Joshua, there's sin in the camp. And until you deal with the sin,
you know what God says to Joshua? I'm not gonna be with you. I'm not gonna fight for
you. I'm not gonna give you the victory. You gotta deal with it. Listen, God will reveal,
he will expose in your life so that you deal with it, so that we deal with it. And we find
that Joseph here, he understood he lived daily in the presence of God. He said, how can I
do this great wickedness and sin against God? I wonder this morning, as we think about this
and we consider the idea, awake to righteousness and sin not. We consider the truth of Psalm
4 that we stand in awe of who? Of God and sin not. This idea that Joseph is living in
the presence of God. Yes, it would be an offense against Potiphar. Yes, it would be
an offense against Potiphar's wife. But ultimately and most importantly, it's an offense against
a holy God. We see the recognition. Number 2, if you're taking notes, I want you to see
the resolve. The resolve. Notice what the Bible tells us in verse number 8, very simply
and I love the first three words, but he refused. But he refused. Isn't that good? And we see
in verse number 8, the resolve of Joseph that he refused and he said unto his master's
wife, behold my master what is not what is with me in the house and he hath committed
all that he hath to my hand. If you're in the habit of writing things in your Bible,
I want you to really think about those words, but he refused. Listen, when sin comes, listen,
you gotta have that, you walk with God, you gotta be able to recognize it, you gotta be
able to see what's going on. And by the way, it's not always as direct as it was, not always
as pointed as it was in our text of Scripture here. Amen? Because sin is deceitful. We find
that the enemy is deceptive and we find here that it's very pointed, it's very clear, but
in your life and in my life, we need to walk with God and we need to have that perception,
we need to understand, listen, your heart is wicked and my heart is wicked. We need
to trust the word of God, we need to trust what God says in his word and we need to follow
it. And we find that the Bible says that he refused. Listen, there's some things as
the people of God that we just need to refuse. Amen? There's some places I'm not gonna go.
There's some things I'm not gonna do. Amen? Why? Because I'm not gonna, I'm not gonna
give any place to the devil. You know, the Bible says in Ephesians that we're not to,
neither give place to the devil. You know what happens sometimes, unfortunately, is
we give place to the devil. We just leave the door open just a little bit, we just kind
of make a little compromise right here. I know I normally wouldn't do this, but I'm
gonna do it and we begin to entertain some of those things and listen, before long, if
we're not careful, sin is a slippery slope. It's a slippery slope. You read throughout
the period of the kings and all of a sudden they're sacrificing their children to Molech.
How in the world did that happen? It didn't start there. It started somewhere way back,
but it's a slippery slope. And there's some things that we gotta refuse. Listen, I refuse
to meet with someone of the opposite sex by myself, 100%. I'm not gonna do it. I've had
people, some of you in here, you know, you've said, can I meet with you as long as my wife
comes or your husband comes? You pick, I don't care. I'll make sure that my wife is available,
but I'm not gonna meet with you by myself. Why? Because I'm not interested. Listen, you
don't have to do anything wrong. You just have to be accused of it. Amen? And so listen,
I just want you to know there's some things that you're gonna have to refuse. And what
did Joseph do? It says that he refused. He refused. That's the resolve. But I want you
to see that it goes further because we talked about the seduction, that it was pointed,
but it was also persistent. We read in verse number 10 that Mrs. Potiphar came day by day.
And yet we read the resolve of Joseph in verse number 11. It says, and it came to pass about
this time that Joseph went into the house to do his business. And there was none of
the men of the house there within. And look at verse number 12. The Bible says, and she
caught him by his garment. And it seems as if, if you read the passage of scripture,
that she's like, this is my opportunity. It's been this persistent attack. And now
Joseph is alone, and I'm gonna take, and I'm gonna just go, and I'm going to grab his garment.
It says, lie with me. But notice what the Bible says at the end of verse number 12.
We see in verse number 8 there that he refused, but in verse number 12 he ran. Hallelujah.
The Bible says this in verse number 12, that he left his garment in her hand and fled and
got him out. Praise God. Pass the Pirate, sing a song. Put on your running shoes, mate.
And if any of you don't know Pass the Pirate, your kids probably listen to it at some point.
And man, that song, put on your running shoes. Listen, sometimes you just gotta run. You
say, well people are gonna say something about me. Who cares? You just need to get out. Amen?
Listen, somebody says he lost his coat. Yes, but he retained his character. Praise God.
Listen, she had his coat and she lied about him, and we'll see that in just a moment.
But listen, it's far better to be lied about than to have actually offended God. Amen?
And we look here and we see that He ran, the Bible tells us in 1 Corinthians chapter 10,
you don't need to turn there, but let me just read it for you.
In 1 Corinthians chapter number 10 and verse number 13, the Bible says,
There hath no temptation taken you, but such as is common to man.
And here's a key that's so important, but God is faithful.
Do you believe God is faithful this morning?
I believe He's faithful.
And I'm so thankful for God's faithfulness.
And we could speak about God's faithfulness in a variety of ways,
but I want you to see contextually that He's talking about when we're facing temptation.
He says that God is faithful to do what?
Who will not suffer to be tempted above that which that you're able,
but will with the temptation also make a way to escape that you may be able to bear it.
I've written in the Marginalized Bible, look for the escape route.
You know what Joseph was doing?
He was looking for the escape route.
We're not going to have time to develop this morning,
but if you were to contrast this portion of Scripture with David and Bathsheba,
you know what David was not looking for?
He was not looking for an escape route.
You know what God was faithful to do for David?
When David inquired about Bathsheba, you know what the servants told him?
She's married.
She's the wife of Uriah the Hittite.
You know what God was doing?
God was providing him with what he needed to know to take the escape route,
but he blew right through it.
Listen, God gives us, He is faithful according to 1 Corinthians 10, 13,
and He'll provide you with the escape route.
The problem is sometimes, sometimes, let me just be transparent this morning,
sometimes people just want to appease their flesh a little bit.
Amen?
Listen, the desires of the flesh are serious.
The flesh and the spirit, they're at enmity one against the other.
And the reality is that there's some, listen,
this is still true when the Bible says that there's pleasure in sin for a season.
Some people just look at the pleasure part of sin,
and they think, well, I'm just going to go ahead and,
no, no, no, God provides a way of escape.
He is faithful, and we've got to look for the escape route.
How do I get out of this situation?
See, he refused, but then he had to run.
He had to run.
Listen, you might need to run from something.
In 1 Corinthians 6 and verse 18, the Bible says,
flee fornication.
In the book of 2 Timothy and chapter 2 and verse number 22,
Paul tells Timothy, flee also youthful lust.
You know, you see in both of those verses of Scripture,
flee, run, get out.
Listen, if you're in a situation, if you're in a setting,
and there's something that, man, the Holy Spirit of God is just telling you
and just bearing witness with your spirit
that there's something not good going on here,
and it's a sinful situation, get out.
Get out.
It's not worth it.
Can I tell you this morning, there's no sin
that's worth hindering your walk with God.
There is no sin, nothing,
that will give you the fullness and the joy
like spending time with Jesus will.
Nothing in his presence is fullness of joy.
You know what sin will do?
It'll leave you wanting.
It'll leave you hurting.
It'll destroy, and it just absolutely causes a mess
of all sorts of things.
It'll cause you to be in a place of regret.
Will it not?
Listen, I never have regretted spending time with Jesus.
I've never regretted being in his presence.
There's fullness of joy.
Praise God.
Noah's Webster's 1828 Dictionary says this about seduction.
I thought it was quite interesting.
It's not the definition for seduction,
but in the definition, he says this.
And I thought it was so good.
I wrote it down word for word.
Here's what he said.
The best safeguard against seduction,
the best safeguard is principle,
the love and purity of holiness,
the fear of God,
and reverence for his commandments.
Praise God.
What a great truth that Noah Webster shares
in that 1828 Dictionary about seduction.
He gives a definition of seduction,
but then talks about what's the best safeguard against?
Having principles.
You know where we get those principles from?
God's Word.
The principles that we find in God's Word.
Love and purity of holiness.
Listen, our God is a thrice holy God.
Holy, holy, holy.
When Isaiah saw him high, holy, and lifted up,
man, it had an impact on him, did it not?
Woe is me, for I am unclean.
We find that the Bible tells us
in the book of Leviticus
and then repeated for us in the New Testament as well,
we find that Peter writes of it,
Be holy, for I am holy.
We're to be holy in all manner of conversation.
We find this idea of love and purity of holiness,
the fear of God.
Listen, I wonder, do we really see God for who he is?
Do we understand that our God is a consuming fire?
Do we understand that it's a fearful thing
to fall into the hands of a living God?
I'm thankful this morning that our God
is gracious and merciful.
Oh, man, I thank him for it every morning.
But you know what else I thank God for?
He's righteous and he's just.
He is.
He's a gracious God, and I've been a recipient of his grace
and his mercy.
Praise God, his mercy endureth forever.
Hallelujah.
But he's a righteous God.
He's a just God.
We find that this idea of the fear of God
and reverence for his commandments.
Do you love God's word?
The psalmist said, Oh, how love I thy law.
It is my meditation all the day.
This book of the law shall not depart out of thy mouth.
Amen?
Thou shalt meditate therein how often day and night.
Joshua 1 and verse 8.
We're going to look at that tonight in more depth.
But I want you to understand this morning
that we see the recognition.
What did Joseph recognize?
Well, he recognized the seduction,
but he recognized the severity.
He recognized the sovereign God.
What did, as we notice the resolve of Joseph,
he refused and then he ran.
What are the results?
Listen, as we look at the text of scripture,
you begin reading in verse 13.
And we find that for the next several verses,
this wicked, evil lie
is put together by Mrs. Potiphar.
It says in verse 13,
And when it came to pass, when she saw
that he had left his garment in her hand
and was fled forth,
she called on the men of the house
and spake unto them, saying,
See, he hath brought in a Hebrew unto us to mock us.
He came in unto me to lie with me,
and I cried with a loud voice.
100% false.
Can I remind you, I said it a few moments ago,
people can accuse you of anything.
Accusations are not always true.
Amen?
I'm going to try to put myself
in a situation where the accusations
aren't going to come, but Joseph was not,
he didn't do anything wrong.
But the accusation comes.
It says in verse number 15,
That I lifted up my voice and cried
that he left his garment with me and fled and got him out.
She laid up his garment by her
until his lord came home,
that's Potiphar comes home, and she spake unto him
according to these words, saying,
The Hebrew servant which thou hast brought unto us
came in unto me to mock me.
And it came to pass as I lifted up my voice
and cried that he left his garment
with me and fled out.
And it came to pass when his master heard the words
of his wife, which she spake unto him,
saying, After this matter did thy servant to me,
notice it says that his wrath was kindled
and your wrath would be kindled as well.
We know the story is false,
but Potiphar at that moment didn't
know that the story was false.
He didn't know this was made up allegation.
We find as we begin
to think about the results and we see what's happened
here and we see the
things that have transpired
in these few moments after this encounter,
the Bible tells us
of the result really
temporarily or from a physical
perspective, a temporal perspective
in verse number 20.
We see Joseph's temporary
imprisonment. The Bible says, And Joseph's
master took him and put him into the prison,
a place where the king's prisoners were bound
and he was there
in the prison.
That's unfortunate,
but it's temporary.
It's temporary.
Joseph had done nothing wrong.
And the only person that really
mattered that knew that is God.
God knew
exactly what happened.
By the way,
we may suffer
in this world,
but we ought not suffer for our own
evil wrongdoing. Amen?
There's a difference
between being imprisoned
like Joseph was. There's a difference
between being in prison like some of the disciples
were than being in prison because
of something that you did that was sinful
and illegal. Amen?
There's a great difference.
And here we find that
Joseph, his temporary imprisonment
is recorded for us in verse number 20.
And I can't imagine Joseph being
in this situation and think about
his life and he'd been lied to about
by his own brothers.
Remember, his dad was the one
that sent him out to see what was going on.
And we find that he suffered greatly
at the hands of his own brothers.
He sold him to slavery and you think about being there in Potiphar's house and things seem to be going well.
I mean God is blessing and man it seems like things are going well.
And then it came to pass and all of these things transpired.
And Joseph is now in prison. We know as you study through the portion of Scripture.
He's there in chapter 41 for at least two more years before Pharaoh has a dream.
But I call it a temporary imprisonment. Why? Because he's not there forever.
Amen? He's going to get lifted out of that prison.
But I want you to understand that we think about the results and sometimes we think about the temporal results as being the most important but they're not.
They're not.
I want you to notice when we think about the results that his testimony was intact.
His testimony was intact. Can I tell you this morning you have a testimony.
I have a testimony.
I wonder how much we really care about the name of our God.
When David sinned and Nathan confronted him he talked about giving occasion to the enemies.
To be able to bring a reproach against his God. Think about that.
We look in the passage of Scripture and we see that his testimony, Joseph's testimony was intact.
And I praise God for this.
And it's important for us to understand as we think about this idea of awake to righteousness and sin not.
Notice in verse 21 the Bible says this. Read it.
But the Lord was with Joseph.
Do you remember how the chapter began?
Do you remember where we started in chapter 39?
The Bible says in verse number 2 and the Lord was with Joseph.
And after all these things had taken place and he's lied about and he's imprisoned temporarily.
You know what the Bible tells us?
But the Lord was with Joseph.
Praise God.
See his testimony was intact.
We see first in verse number 21 that the Lord was with him.
I'm so thankful for the presence of God.
I can't imagine, I don't understand exactly all that took place in that prison cell.
And how God in his sweetness and in only the way in which he can brought great comfort to Joseph in that moment.
Because the Bible says that the Lord was with Joseph.
I think Joseph knew that.
I think he experienced the presence of God.
Have you ever been in a place where you experienced the presence of God?
I'm not talking about some spooky Pentecostal kind of thing.
I'm just talking about you spent time with God and you knew you were in the presence of God.
Amen.
Listen I'm thankful that our God inhabits the praises of his people.
Our God is pleased when we desire to spend that time with him.
We heard last week as Brother Beal preached that message about come here.
That we're to draw nigh to God but then what? He draws nigh to us.
Amen praise the Lord.
Remember with Noah when God tells Noah come into the ark that represents for us the fact that God was already there in the ark.
He didn't tell him go into the ark like he was on the outside and tell him to go in.
No God says come into the ark.
And I'm so thankful that we can have time and fellowship with our God.
And here the Bible says that the Lord was with Joseph.
And then the Bible tells us in verse number 21 and showed him mercy.
And showed him mercy.
Again Joseph spent some time in prison.
It wasn't immediately that things were resolved for Joseph.
It wasn't that things were found out with regard to how Potiphar's wife had lied about him and all those sorts of things.
But we find that God showed him mercy.
God was with him and God showed him mercy.
And then we find that the Bible says in verse 21.
Notice it says and gave him favor in the sight of the keeper of the prison.
God gave him favor.
God was blessing this man. Why?
Because he was innocent.
Because he had done no transgression.
He had not sinned against God.
Oh the temptation came.
He recognized it.
And there was resolve.
And he said how can I do this great wickedness and sin against God.
And we find that God allowed Joseph to suffer these things.
But then God is with him and his testimony is intact.
And we read a portion of scripture like Genesis chapter 39.
And we understand historically the event, the account and what transpires.
And we can look at it and we can understand that we too in the moment of temptation we can refuse it.
And we can run and we can keep our testimony.
Amen.
Your testimony is important.
There are people that know that you're a Christian.
I hope there are some people that know that you've tried to share the gospel with them.
Amen.
Can I tell you that when you sin, when you fall, it affects other people.
None of us are on an island to ourselves.
We have influence.
And it's absolutely imperative that we understand yes most importantly it's an offense against our holy God.
But I want you to recognize the importance of your testimony.
Your family, your kids, your church, community.
It's a big deal.
It's serious.
And we find that God was with them and God showed them mercy and God gave them favor.
The Bible says in verse 22,
And the keeper of the prison committed to Joseph's hand all the prisoners that were in the prison.
And whatsoever they did there, he was the doer of it.
The keeper of the prison looked not to anything that was under his hand, because why?
The Lord was with him.
That which he did the Lord made it to prosper.
You know it's interesting.
If you read Genesis 39 verses 1 through 6 as we did by way of introduction.
And if you read Genesis chapter number 39 verses 21 through 23.
You see the same very things about his walk with God.
God's with them. God's blessing them.
Things are prospering.
And in the middle you got this terrible situation that takes place.
But I'm so thankful that Joseph retained his integrity.
He kept his testimony.
Now that's not by his own doing.
That's with God's help and by God's grace.
Can I remind you that Jesus said without me you can do nothing.
Listen you're no match for the devil.
I'm no match for the devil.
But he told us to put on the whole armor of God.
Be strong in the Lord and the power of his might.
Amen.
And we find that as we follow the admonition from Ephesians chapter number 6.
That God will allow us to have that victory.
Listen we sing the song victory in Jesus.
Praise God.
But thanks be to God which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus Christ.
Let me remind you of what Paul said.
Take your Bible and turn to Acts 24 if you will.
Paul's standing here and giving an account.
Once again before many in these chapters as he's there.
And here in Acts chapter 24 he's specifically dealing with taking some time there before Felix.
And we find here in Acts chapter 24 that Paul reveals something to us about his heart and his perspective.
That is so important for us to consider this morning.
In light of the idea awake to righteousness and sin not.
Notice what the Bible says and I don't have time to read through the entirety.
And so let's just jump down right there.
Let's look at verse 2 and then we'll jump down to verse 16.
In verse 2 it says and when he was called forth a turtle list began to.
Notice what the Bible says.
Accuse him.
Saying seeing that by thee we enjoy great quietness.
And that very worthy deeds are done unto this nation by thy providence.
You go through and we find that they say in verse number 5 the accusation is that they found this man Paul to be a pestilent fellow.
A mover of sedition among the Jews throughout the world.
A ring leader of the sect of the Nazarenes.
I mean he's been accused of all kinds of things.
And Paul's able to stand up and give his defense.
He tells them in verse number 13 neither can they prove the things whereof they now accuse me.
But then I want you to notice what he says in verse number 16.
He says and herein do I exercise myself.
Now I know sometimes the word exercise can be a negative word.
I don't want to exercise right.
Like it's bad physically.
He's not talking about physical exercise.
But the word still carries with it the idea of laboring and striving.
You know exercise is work.
It is.
You go and you work out.
You go and exercise.
It's work.
It's labor.
He says and herein do I exercise myself.
I'm laboring.
I'm striving.
I'm putting forth effort for a purpose.
Notice what he says.
To have always.
Now that's an important word.
To have always a conscience void of offense toward God and toward men.
That's exemplary.
That is a perspective that is necessary for God's people today to have.
He says I'm laboring.
I'm putting in the work.
I'm striving as I'm walking with God.
Abide in me Jesus said.
And as I'm walking with the Lord and as I'm studying his word.
As I'm reading his word.
As I'm spending time with God in prayer.
That I'm doing these things.
Why?
Because I desire to have fellowship with him.
And to have that relationship grown closer together with my Savior.
But he says to have always a conscience.
Notice it says always.
We sing the song.
Nothing between my soul and my Savior.
When I think about that hymn I always think about this verse of Scripture in Acts 20.
24 and verse 16. Because really, if I were to summarize it, you know what Paul's saying?
I don't want there to be anything between me and my God. I don't want there to be anything
between me and my Savior. I want that communion with my Savior to be sweet, that I can enter
into His presence. Listen, you understand physically as we have relationships here on
earth, if you have some kind of aught with somebody that you have a relationship in life,
a spouse, a child, a co-worker, a whoever it might be, and there's some kind of aught
between you, you don't really enter into their presence often easily. Sometimes you might
actually avoid. And here Paul says to have always a conscience void of offense, number
one, toward God. And by the way, if we have our conscience void of offense toward God,
we'll be going a long way to have it void of offense toward men. And again, it's living
in the presence of God. That's what Joseph did in Egypt. He said, how can I do this great
wickedness and sin against God? God sees everything. He knows your thoughts. I don't know if there's
any sin in your life, but God does. And here's the admonition this morning. Awake to righteousness
and sin not. Sin is serious, deceitful. I keep saying deceptive and deceitful together.
And I'll just keep trying to make that word up, amen? And sin is, it's deceptive. It really
is. And your testimony in God's name is important. That we awake to righteousness and sin not.
By God's grace and with His help, I'm going to daily, you know, I pray, God help me to
be crucified with Christ today. Help me today. You know what the Bible says? Great promise.
Walk in the Spirit and ye shall not fulfill the lust of the flesh. It didn't say that
the flesh won't lust. It just said that if you walk in the Spirit, you shall not fulfill
the lust of the flesh. Listen, we need some Spirit-filled Christians that are walking
in the Spirit, that are concerned about being spiritual, being right with God. Awake to
righteousness and sin not. Let's pray. Father, how we love you this morning. God, I pray
that you'd help me and help us to see the importance of this truth of awaking to righteousness.
Lord, as we have opportunity to look at the life of Joseph, help us to be challenged by
those things that transpired in his life. Help us to be alert, awake, and aware of those
things around us that we'd be able to recognize as Joseph did. The temptations that were coming.
Lord, help us to refuse, to have that resolve that Joseph had. To be resolved, to refuse
and to run and to be more concerned about our walk with you than the pleasure of sin.
God, we trust you with the results. I know that accusations can come even as they did
for Joseph, but I'm thankful that you've given us in your Word the truth of what transpired
in his life. Just a little while after this event, he's restored and he's put in place
of authority. And God, you continue to use him and I'm thankful for that. And I pray
that you'd help us to have our testimony intact, that we would not bring reproach against
thy name, Lord. That we would not give opportunity to the enemy to say anything negative about
you, Lord, our wonderful Savior. I pray that if there's someone here that's not saved,
that today would be the day of their salvation. Pray for believers, Lord, would you help us
to understand the importance of walking with you and seeing you high, holy and lifted up
to truly stand in awe of you. I pray that in the moments of invitation that you would
help us to be responsive, Lord, to how you've spoken to our hearts. And we'll thank you
for what you'll do for us in Christ's name we pray. Would you stand with me? Heads are
bowed, eyes are closed and at the end of our service we have an invitation and we just
give you an opportunity to respond to the Lord. I trust God's used his Word to speak
to his people this morning. I prayed for that early this morning and I trust that God's
answered that prayer and as God's worked and spoken to you through his Word, maybe you
come to this altar, make your seat an altar and you just talk to the Lord. Maybe there's
some things in your life that you need to get right, I don't know. Maybe you just want
to come and pray and ask God to help you to stay right, to keep your eyes on him, the
author and finisher of our faith. As Kimberly plays, the altar is open.